Finding Aid for the Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records 1986-1992 LSC.2203
UCLA Library Special Collections
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records
1986-1994
UCLA Library Special Collections
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change
LSC.2203
1.2 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC) is a national organization for lesbians over the age of 60. Using education and public discourse, the core mission of OLOC is to combat ageism and increase the visibility of older lesbians. The majority of the materials in the collection are about the 1987 West Coast Conference and Celebration and its planning and programming. Also included is correspondence between members, as well as people on the steering committee.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Acquisition Information
Provenance unknown. This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library.
Sponsor
The June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA is an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW), and the UCLA Library. These collections expand the pool of primary source materials available to researchers and to the community at large. This partnership was initiated by CSW and is funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) to inventory, organize, preserve, and digitize more than eighty Mazer collections pertaining to lesbian and feminist activism and writings.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9973847793606533
Biography
After the publication of the book Look Me in the Eye: Old Women, Aging and Ageism by Barbara MacDonald and Cynthia Rich, a group of lesbians was inspired and empowered to start the First West Coast Conference and Celebration for Old Lesbians in Southern California. The event was held at the California State University, Dominguez Hills Campus in Carson, California in April 1987.
Out of the group that attended this conference as well as its follow-up in 1989, a group of sixteen lesbians went on to form an organization. At the first organizational meeting, a name was chosen, a statement of purpose drafted, tasks assigned, a coordinator designated and future meetings scheduled. The Old Lesbian Organizing Committee (later renamed Old Lesbians Organizing for Change) had begun.
Participation was strictly limited to lesbians 60 years of age and older. However, OLOC has always welcomed the support of younger lesbians while maintaining the need for separate space.
OLOC quickly established a newsletter with a national reach and began enrolling members. Early efforts were concentrated on educational materials on ageism, using familiar and effective consciousness raising techniques. These materials were pooled and published in The Facilitator's Handbook: Confronting Ageism: Consciousness Raising for Lesbians 60 and Over.
OLOC was a strong and highly visible part of the National Lesbian Conference in Atlanta 1991 as well as the March on Washington in 1993.
By 1992, OLOC sought and gained non-profit status, incorporating in the state of Texas. It achieved tax exempt status in 1994.
In 1996, OLOC held its first National Gathering, held on the campus of University of Minnesota at Minneapolis. In 1999, it held its second gathering in San Francisco, CA. The third was in 2002, again in Minnesota. The conferences are now held every other year.
OLOC continues to produce a quarterly newsletter called the OLOC Reporter, coordinate biennial gatherings, participate in the Old Lesbian Oral Herstory Project and produce a line of age-positive, women-friendly greeting cards.
Scope and Content
This collection contains organizational materials for Old Lesbians Organizing for Change (OLOC), an organization devoted to combating ageism through education and advocacy. The majority of the materials in the collection deal with the West Coast Conference and Celebration, its planning and programming. Also included is correspondence between members as well as people on the steering committee.
Organization and Arrangement
Materials arranged by type and in chronological order.
Related Material
Barbara Macdonald papers (Collection 2159). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Elaine Mikels papers (Collection 1954). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Degania Golove papers (Collection 1984). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Ester Bentley papers (Collection 1981). Available at Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Papers of Cynthia Rich and Barbara Macdonald, 1893-2004 MC 505. Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
Aging -- Social aspects -- United States.; Ageism -- United States.; June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives; June L. Mazer Lesbian Archive at UCLA; Old Lesbians Organizing for Change -- Archives
- Correspondence: Internal, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence between members and various committees of OLOC, mostly about the first West Coast Celebration By and For Old Lesbians that took place in April 1987 in Santa Monica, California.
- West Coast Celebration newspaper clippings, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  Articles, blurbs and reviews of the West Coast Celebration and Conference By and For Old Lesbians which took place in Santa Monica, California in 1987 as well as related correspondence.
- West Coast Celebration expenses, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Receipts, invoices and summaries of expenses including preparation, publicity and programming costs.
- West Coast Celebration publicity, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Press releases, advertisements, and articles that served as publicity for the West Coast Celebration throughout 1986 and 1987.
- West Coast Celebration mailing lists, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  Mailing lists and materials for members and interested parties of OLOC and of the West Coast Celebration.
- West Coast Celebration photograph release forms, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Signed release and permissions forms for photographs taken at the West Coast Conference on behalf of OLOC.
- West Coast Celebration grant applications, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Grant applications in support of the West Coast Conference.
- West Coast Celebration programming, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Programming information, schedules, itineraries and details concerning the day to day logistics of the West Coast Conference.
- Correspondence: Members, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Correspondence to and from members of OLOC concerning activities of the national organization as well as regional parties.
- West Coast Celebration and Conference of Old Lesbians II, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Programming information, correspondence and planning documents, photographs, and a bibliography on old lesbians.
- Correspondence: Shevy Healey, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Correspondence [by] Shevy Healey, some related to OLOC, some personal. Included is a note concerning the relationship of the letters to the organization.
- OLOC newsletters, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1, Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  Newsletters for OLOC detailing events, educational materials and important logistical information.
- OLOC sign-in sheets, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Sign in sheets from gatherings and meetings of OLOC.
- National Lesbian Conference, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Programming information, flyers, planning documents and promotional materials from OLOC's participation in the National Lesbian Conference.
- Administrative files, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Includes bylaws, organizational information, norms and mission statements. Included are drafts and completed versions.
- Correspondence: Degania Golove, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Correspondence with Degania Golove on behalf of OLOC.
- Summer Gathering materials, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Materials for the summer gathering of 1996 in Minneapolis, Minnesota. This includes planning documents, correspondence, programming information and conference materials.
- Flyers, circa 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Flyers for events and gatherings.
- Educational materials, circa 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Essays, one-sheets and handouts concerning the mission and goals of OLOC and the importance of combating ageism.